Amlan Kusum Chakraborty

63/26 Dum Dum Road, Akashdeep – B-3/2, Kolkata-700074

*****+91 7003687635/9836675762

E-mail: amlan.mail@rediffmail.com



In a nutshell

O A journalist of the largest circulated vernacular daily turned a management graduate. Working as a strategy analyst at present, with more than eight years of experience as a national buying and merchandising manager in a national retail chain. Having a thorough knowledge of food and non-food retailing. An avid reader and a passionate writer.

Work Experience

Current Employer : IFB Agro Industries

Duration: January 2020- Present

Designation: Retail Strategy Analyst- Aquashop

Key Responsibilities:

- Overhauling and restructuring the retail strategy of Aquashop (An IFB Agro initiative—One stop destination for fish feed, farm equipments, farm medicines and allied things related to aquaculture)
- o Rural marketing and strategizing
- Driving footfalls, increasing the number of bills and average bill value thorough the unexplored routes

Previous Employer: Spencer's Retail Ltd (RP-Sanjiv Goenka Group)--Corporate

Duration : August 2011- January 2020

Designation:

Merchandising and Buying Manager-Home Care [Aug'18-Jan '20] Merchandising and Buying Manager-Branded Bakery [Apr'17-Jul'18] Buying Manager-Dairy [Aug'11-Mar'17]

Key Responsibilities:

- o *Category analysis and strategic decision making:* Analyzing the causative factors for category growth and downfall, taking corrective actions wherever necessary.
- o *Budgeting:* Fabricating the targeted category sales & margin numbers across the country, with a special focus on same store sales growth.

- o *Procurement planning:* Sourcing quality products on the basis of volume consumption growth and consumer preference.
- o *Ensuring stock availability:* Presenting a rich assortment of products to our valuable customers with an eye on imported assortments as well.
- o *National coordination:* Keeping in touch with our regional teams on day to day affairs, intervening with the concerned when an issue is escalated.
- o *Sales & margin projection:* To feel the pulse of the category and to observe whether the performance till date is in tune with the budget numbers.
- Brand Management: Effective handling of more than hundred brands, focusing on regional brands during regional celebrations, working on market share across the brands.
- o *Promotion negotiation:* Ensuring customer happiness by chalking out monthly buying cycle consumer offers, deep discounting during the weeks of 26th Jan, 15th Aug, Diwali etc.
- o *Management of competitive pricing:* For like to like products, looking at the prices across the retail chains and driving the level best to offer the products at the 'best' prices to our customers.
- o Assortment benchmarking: Studying the assortments of our competitors periodically and fill the assortment gap on a war footing if needed.
- o *Enhancement of visibility income:* Branding of chiller headers, freezers, end caps, floor stacks etc.
- Implementation of automated replenishment system: Automating the ordering system on the basis of historical sales data and shelf fits, minimizing the human intervention in day to day ordering. Single handedly implemented ARS for Dairy category.
- Vendor management: Managing more than two hundred vendors, doing the needful
 if they are stuck up somewhere, coordinating across verticals for speedy resolution
 of vendor related issues.
- o TOT negotiation
- Coordination for ATL/BTLs
- As a special project, single handedly implemented Automatic Replenishment System for Dairy, across business locations.

Previous Employer: Indian Chamber of Commerce, Kolkata

Duration: May 2011-July 2011

Role : Senior Executive, Team Agribusiness

Description:

- Strategic analysis of sectoral growth and downfall
- Coordination of national events
- Management of sponsors
- Content Management, Press Release

Previous Employer: ABP Pvt. Ltd (Anandabazar Patrika)

Duration : 1 Yr 9 months (Nov 2007 to Aug 2009)

Role : Correspondent, Sub Editor

Description:

- Special focus on science journalism
- o Interviewing eminent personalities
- Covering national level press conferences
- Writing and editing news stories
- o Pagination and coordination

Educational Qualification

Post Graduation	Post Graduate Diploma in Management
2009-2011	
	Agri-Business & Plantation Management, Indian Institute of
	Plantation Management, Bangalore. (An autonomous
	organization promoted by Ministry of Commerce & Industry,
	Govt. of India)65%
Graduation	B.Tech
2003-2007	Food Technology, Techno India, Kolkata, affiliated to West Bengal University of Technology. DGPA 7.65
<u>H.S.C</u>	Dum Dum Kishore Bharati High School (West Bengal Council
2001-2003	for Higher Secondary Education), 72.9%
Secondary 2001	Dum Dum Kishore Bharati High School (West Bengal Board for Secondary Education), 88.1%

Computer Awareness

- MS Office
- o SAP (Retail Module-end user)

Achievements

- Achieved 'Star of the Month' in FMCG in Spencer's Retail Ltd twice (Dec'17 & Mar'19)
- o Anchored the cultural as well as formal functions during post graduate programme.
- o Regularly contribute features for All India Radio, Kolkata. A regular talker for the public broadcaster.
- Obtained 98.1 percentile with a composite score of 743.5 in MAT dated 07.12.2008.
- Ranked among the top 12 percentilers in the 3rd National IT Aptitude Test (NITAT) conducted by NIIT (Jan,2007).

• Won the 1st prize in extempore competition and 2nd prize in debate competition in 'West Bengal Rajya Yuva Utsav', organized by the Government of West Bengal (1998).

Areas of Interest

- Creative writing: Authored more than 15 short stories, numerous cover stories, post editorials, features for leading newspapers/magazines/webzines. Works appeared in ABP, Sangbad Pratidin, Bartaman, Ei Samay, Aajkal, Uttarbanga Sangbad, Bangalive.com, Tathyakendra to name a few. Some of my works were highly acclaimed by the literary fraternity of Bengal.
- o First compilation of a set of short stories has been **published as a book** in Kolkata International Book Fair, 2019.
- Second book is a compilation of features. Launched in Kolkata International Book Fair, 2020.
- o Regularly contribute to the most of the leading dailies and magazines of West Bengal, on invitation.
- o Publicly praised as one of the shining young writers by a few best-selling senior authors/journalists of Bengal.

Additional Information

Date of Birth: 23rd November, 1985, Kolkata **Languages Known**: Bengali, English, Hindi